A Guide to the Provisional Army of Virginia, Recruiting Officer Records, 1861
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Provisional Army of Virginia, Recruiting Officer Records, 1861
Library of Virginia
38889
.55 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905 (no other acquisition information available).
Biographical/Historical Information
An ordinance to provide for the organization of the Provisional Army of Virginia was passed on April 27, 1861 by the Virginia Convention. Robert E. Lee was appointed "commander of the military and naval forces of Virginia" on April 23 with a commission as major general in the Provisional Army and the Volunteer Forces of Virginia. The Provisional Army was to consist of two regiments of artillery, eight regiments of infantry, a regiment of riflemen, and a regiment of cavalry. Only one battalion, however, the 1st Battalion Virginia Infantry (Irish Battalion), and one independent artillery company under Capt. Greenlee Davidson was recruited in 1861. Joseph Selden was nominated by Governor Letcher on the recommendation of Gen. Lee as Lt. Col. of Volunteers on April 17. Selden was later named superintendent of the recruiting service for the Provisional Army. On July 17, L.P. Walker, CSA Secretary of War, wrote to George W. Munford, Secretary of the Commonwealth, regarding the accounts of Joseph Selden and the recruiting service. In this letter, Walker ordered that the service be discontinued as the Confederate States relies on volunteer forces (War of the Rebellion, 4th Series, I:484). It appears that the recruiting service continued until the end of September 1861.
Scope and Content Information
Contains vouchers, accounts current, receipts, financial statements, correspondence, abstracts, returns, and musters of recruits. These materials were submitted to the Auditing Board by various recruiting officers of the Provisional Army of Virginia in 1861. The vouchers document the expenses incurred by these officers in performing their duty. The expenses include such items as room & board, transportation, printing posters, stationery, etc. The abstracts summarize the information from numerous vouchers and include the date of payment, on what account, and costs in dollars and cents. Noteworthy are the two musters of recruits. One of these musters was made by E.S. Hutter, Jr., and the other by William E. Harrison. The musters include the names of the recruits, rank, date of recruitment, place of enlistment, physical description (hair & eye color, height & weight), place of birth, occupation, and age.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by the name of the recruiting officer.
Contents List
- Provisional Army of Virginia, Recruiting Officer Records, 1861
  - Barton, C.M., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chilton, R.H., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Coltrane, B., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dunn, Thomas R., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gibson, William E., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gregory, W.R., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Harrison, William E., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hart, T.G., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Harvie, J.B., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Horner, George B., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hutter, E.S., Jr., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Jones, James Y., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ker, James, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - McCarty, J.W., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Overton, William, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Selden, J., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Slaughter, P.P., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Tabb, W.B., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Turner, J.A., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Williams, L.R., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Barton, C.M. - Accounts current (Oversize), 1861 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Coltrane, B.E. - Accounts current (Oversize), 1861 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gibson, W.E. - Accounts current (Oversize), 1861 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hart, T.G. - Accounts current (Oversize), 1861 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Harrison, William E. - Recruits enlisted for the Provisional Army (Oversize), 1861 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Horner, George B. - Accounts current (Oversize), 1861 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hutter, E.S., Jr. - Recruits enlisted for the Provisional Army (Oversize), 1861 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Jones, James Y. - Accounts current (Oversize), 1861 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - McCarty, J.W. - Accounts current (Oversize), 1861 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Selden, J. - Quarterly return of stores (Oversize), 1861 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Selden, J. - Statement of funds (Oversize), 1861 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Turner, T.A. - Accounts current (Oversize), 1861 (Box 2, Folder 12)